Milan Aleksić

Last updated: 02/07/2024

Personal

Born on 21/12/1983, Smederevo (Serbia), living in Koekelberg (Belgium) since 2011. I have dual citizenship of Belgium and Serbia.

My website is aleksic.dev, email is milan@aleksic.dev and Twitter account is: milanaleksic. I am fairly active on github.com/milanaleksic. I also have a LinkedIn account if you'd like to connect with me.

Education

Dipl. Ing. Computer Science & Engineering (2008) from *University of Belgrade* (Serbia), Faculty of Electrical Engineering (ETF)

"NARIC - Vlaanderen" recognized diploma as M.Sc.

Spoken languages

- Serbian (mother tongue)
- English (fluent)
- **Dutch** (C1 Effectiveness 1)
- French (A2, basic level)

Keywords

Java, Go, AWS, Python, PostgreSQL, MySQL

Experience

Senior Software Engineer @ Soda (Belgium)

Place: Remote/Brussels, Belgium

Period: **2020-...**

Projects:

- soda.io Cloud Backend (founding) engineer
 - Programming languages: (mostly) Java, Python and cloud development on AWS using Terraform
 - Tasked with backend feature development, guidance and documentation. One of the first ("founding") engineers and therefore I witnessed all the pivoting, market adaptations, surprising platform usage patterns, product evolution, became the company MySQL perf guy, guided or advised all the Soda Cloud development efforts...
 - Helped the company grow 100x in customers and revenue over 5 years without high-profile incidents or downtime of the Soda Cloud product
 - Beyond product and engineering impact, also introduced discipline in performance analysis and monitoring via DataDog, incident management and other operational concerns of the Soda Cloud
- Tool maker role:
 - deep incident analysis tool using custom dynamically created trace profiles datadog-exporter
 (Go, Datadog API, SQLite, Perfetto)
 - internal tool for various admin tasks, including feature flip management, admin API back-channel, environment setup, DB dynamic password feneration, framework for complex migrations, etcdopy (Python3, Okta SSO+MFA, boto3)
- Broad exposure to data sources while helping bootstrap Soda SQL: PostgreSQL, Redshift, Athena, Spark

Expert Software Engineer @ TomTom (Belgium)

Place: Ghent, Belgium

Period: **2017-2020**

CCE Team Feature development and maintenance of various core systems and applications in MPU Core Coverage Creation & Extension team

Projects:

- MLF library: authored code-generated Java wrapper around GDAL OpenFileGDB (later extended to PostGIS and GeoPackage).
 - Custom ANTLR grammar for extended validation, Python/Markdown doc generator
- Sinatra: Led migration of a complex process into AWS for GIS source data digestion
 - PostgreSQL RDS, Spring Boot 2, SQS, ECS, Terraform, Vue.js
- Pupin: created machine learning cloud service for data classification (plural junctions problem)
 - Training: PostGIS, Python, Scikit-Learn, XGBoost, (Geo)Pandas, Jupyter
 - Online+Batch prediction: Terraform / AWS ECS, Spring Boot 2, XGBoost, REST
- Dumbo: migration of internal heavily used batch processing tool into the cloud
 - AWS Batch, ECS, PostgreSQL, S3, X-Ray; Spring Boot 2, Terraform, Python, Jenkins
- Excelsior: process orchestration service
 - States Language implementation (spec only), ECS+Lambda, Java 11, Python 3

Hermes team Feature development on new long-term systems and applications in *Hermes* team

Projects:

- Nozem: always-up-to-date OpenStreetMap ingestion service into core TomTom data layer
 - Kafka, PostgreSQL, Python, Spring Boot, Jenkins
- Lego: automated OpenStreetMap features ingestion
 - Kubernetes on Azure Cloud, Python, Java, QGIS Python plugins

{Senior, Lead} Software Engineer @ Basware (Belgium)

Place: Aalst, Belgium

Period: **2013-2017**

Projects:

- Basware Network Portal: Full-stack development role on online and internal services
 - Tech stack: Play2, Scala, Java8, MongoDB, Spring, Chef, Go
 - Rewritten core validation business rules implementation (Java)
- Basware e-Archiving: DevOps lead-in-charge and one of lead developers
 - Tech stack: CloudFormation, Jenkins, Bash, AWS CLI
 - Cloud stack: Java Lambda functions, API GW, S3, DynamoDB, SQS, Splunk
- Norsu (Groovy, Cucumber, Gradle): Cross-systems end-to-end testing
- Business Metrics dashboards (Akka and Dashing.io)
- Migration of legacy Resin applications to Tomcat cluster
 - Oracle DB, JSP, RMI, Ant, Tomcat, Apache2
- HAL9000 (Golang): Flowdock bot (CI/CD automation helper for 100+ developers)

Previous work experience

2014: Freelance Consultant (remote) @ Gtech UK (*Brussels*, *Belgium*)

2011-2013: Software consultant @ Cronos (Belgium) (Brussels, Belgium)

2009-2011: Software Engineer II @ Gtech G2 Sports Betting (Belgrade, Serbia)

2007-2009: Java Developer @ Arius (Belgrade, Serbia)

2006: Intern software developer @ ESAProjekt (Katowice, Poland)

Selected open source projects

- Advent of Code 2023 (Zig)
- Github Helper CLI (Rust, Github API)
 - epic issues dependency graph handling, branch names and other "my flow" helpers
- Personal Web site (Hugo, Cloudflare Pages)
- Advent of Code 2018 (Go)
- gomakefiles (Makefile, Bash)
 - Reusable Makefile files which allow cross CI/CD Go compilation with many useful tools
- Igor (Go Lambda, Vue.js, Google+, CloudFront, Cognito, DynamoDB)
 - "I am away" Flowdock bot, deployed via Semaphore.ci + CloudFormation

Selected closed source personal projects

- Home Laboratory
 - Hybrid cluster (aarch64/amd64 debian/ubuntu, home/Oracle cloud) connected using Tailscale.
 NAS included
 - Infra as code: Ansible for foundational setup of bare new nodes, Nomad/Consul for container scheduling (25+ services like Gitea, Minecraft, yarr, etc.)
 - Monitoring via Grafana, InfluxDB, Grafana Loki and Tempo
- Thought Train (Go, PostgreSQL, ANTLR, NATS, Vue.js / htmx, Svelte, Flutter, Bootstrap)
 - Feature-rich web page content extraction & book annotation distributed service
 - Search Query grammar, Pulumi-based AWS cloud setup
 - mobile applications (Android, iOS) and Chrome Extension
- Batler (Go)
 - Telegram bot I use for home automation tasks like turning on/off my workhorse laptop, Windows
 VM and main notification pipeline
- Novinarnica (Go, Google OAuth, Batler)
 - Content crawler and CBR packager of magazines from www.novinarnica.net

Miscellaneous

Public talks

 (BeScala) Introducing a reactive Scala-Akka based system in a Java centric company with Jeroen Verellen, 2015